欢迎回来, 这是我们长系列的第一个视频
Welcome back. This is the first video in our long series of the
编译器的实现, 上次的调用编译器有五个阶段。
implementation of compilers, The call from last time that a compiler has five phases.
我们首先要讲的是词汇分析这可能会让我们
We're gonna begin by talking about lexical analysis and this will probably take us
3到4个视频至少要讲完然后我们会继续讲
three to four videos to get through at least and then we'll, we will be moving on
为了其他阶段, 让我们从一个小的代码片段开始。
in order to the other phases. Let's start by looking at a small code fragment. The
词法分析的目的是将这段代码划分为词汇单元
goal of lexical analysis is to divide this piece of code up. Into lexical units so
比如关键字如果变量名i, n, j和关系运算符
things like the keyword if the variable names i, n, j and the relational operator
双等号, 等等, 现在作为一个人, 这是。我们上节课讲过
double-equals and so on. Now as a human being this is. As we discussed last time
这是一件很容易做的事情因为有各种各样的视觉线索
this is a very easy thing to do because there are all kinds of visual clues about
单位位于不同单位之间的边界, 但a
where the units lie Where the boundaries between the different units lie but a
像词汇分析器这样的程序, 它没有那种奢侈, 事实上
program like lexical analyzer. It doesn't have that kind of luxury. In fact what
分析者会看到的是更像这样的东西, 所以
the, what the likes of analyzer will see is something that looks more like this. So
这里我重写了, 代码就像一个字符串, 包含了所有的空格符号
here I overwritten, the code out just as a string, with all the white space symbols
从这个表达式中, 这是一个线性字符串,
included and is from, from this representation, this is a linear string,
你可以把它看成是词汇分析器必须工作的文件中的字节
you can think of this as bytes in the file that the lexical analyzer has to work and
它会穿过, 在不同的单位之间放置分隔物, 所以,
it's going to mark through, placing dividers between the different units. So,
它会意识到那里有一个分裂, 在白色空间和
it will recognize that there's a division there, between the white space and the
关键字, 然后是关键字后面的除法还有更大的空间, 打开
keyword. Then a division after the keyword and there's more a wide space, the open
paren, i, 另一个宽的空间, 双等号, 等等
paren, the i, another wide space, double equals and so on and it goes through
画出这些线, 把弦插入到它的词汇单元中, 所以我不会
drawing these lines diving up. The, the string into its lexical unit, So I won't
完成整个事情, 但你应该明白, 现在, 它不仅仅是放置这些东西
finish the whole thing but you should get the idea. Now, it doesn't just place these
但是字符串中的分规, 它不只是识别子字符串, 它也
dividers in the string however. It doesn't just recognize the substrings. It also
需要根据角色的角色对字符串的不同元素进行分类。
needs to classify the different elements of the string according to their role. We
调用这些令牌类, 或者有时, 我将其命名为令牌的类。
call these token classes. Or sometimes, I'll just call it the class of the token.
在英语中, 这些角色是名词, 动词, 形容词, 好的
And in English, these roles are things like noun, verb, adjective. Okay and there
是, e是更多的, 至少是更多的, 在编程中
is, ther e are many more or at least or some more. And in the programming
语言, 类, 令牌类都是标识符,
language, the classes, the token classes would be things like identifiers,
关键词, 我, 然后是单独的语法比如一个开放的paren或者一个闭合的
Keywords. I, and then individual pieces of syntax like an open paren or a close
帕伦, 这些是他们自己的课程, A, 数字, 还有, 这里
paren, those are the classes by themselves. A, numbers. And again, there
是更多的类但是有一组很厚的类, 每一个都有
are more classes but there's a thick set of classes and each one of these
对应于一些可能出现在程序中的字符串。
corresponds to some set of strings that could appear in a program. So token
类对应于一组字符串, 而听不清字符串可以被描述
classes correspond to sets of strings, And [inaudible] strings can be described
相对直接的, 例如, 标识符的记号类
relatively straightforwardly so for example. The token class of identifiers in
大多数编程语言可能类似于字符串或字符串
most programming languages might be something like strings of letters or
数字, 从一个字母开始, 例如, 一个变量名或标识符
digits, starting with a letter. So for example, a variable name or identifier
可以是a1, 也可以是f00也可以是b17, 所有这些
could be something like a1 or it could be f00 or it could be, b17, all of those
会是有效的标识符通常, 它们会是额外的字符
would be, be valid identifiers and often, often they'll be additional characters
这允许标识符但这是基本思想, 非常, 通常是主要的
that allowed identifiers but that's the basic idea, Very, very often The main
限制标识符必须开始, 有一个字母, 一个整数
restriction identifiers that they have to start, with a letter, An integer and
一个整数的典型定义是一个非空的数字串。
typical definition of an integer is a non-empty string of digits. So, something
比如0或12, 好的, 一个接着两个我应该说实际上是一串
like zero or twelve. Okay. One followed by two I should say is actually a string of
这个例子中的数字, 是的, 实际上它是承认一些数字
number in this case. And, and yeah, it is actually whether admit some numbers you
可能不会想到, 像001这样的东西会是一个数字的有效表示
might not think of. Things like 001 would be a valid representation of a number or
根据这个定义, 即使00也可以是一个有效的整数。
even 00 could be a valid integer according to this definition. Keywords are typically
这是一组固定的词所以这里我列出了一些, 如果, 开始,
just a fix set of reserved words and so here I've listed a few, else, if, begin,
等等, 然后白色空间本身就是一个令牌类所以我们不得不说
and so on. And then white space as itself a token class so we actually have to say
在这个字符串中这是程序的表示每个字符都是
in that string which is the representation of the program what every character in
这个字符串, 什么令牌或者什么令牌类它是每个子串的一部分
that string, what token or what token class it's a part of. What every substring
是其中的一部分, 包括空白区域, 例如, 如果我们有一个级数
is a part of and that includes the white space. So, for example if we have a series
在三个空格中, 如果我说if然后是一个开放的paren我有三个空格
of three blanks, if I say if and then an open paren and I have three blanks in
这里, 这三个空白的s会被组合成白色的空间, 所以我们的目标是
here, these three blank s would be grouped together as white space. So the goal of
词法分析是根据程序的角色对程序的子串进行分类。
lexical analysis is to classify substrings of the program according to their role.
这是令牌类, 好吗？它是一个关键字, 一个变量标识符, 然后
This is the, the token class, okay? Is it a keyword, a variable identifier, And then
要将这些令牌与解析器通信, 因此, 在这里画一个图, 让我们
to communicate these tokens, to the parser. So, drawing a picture here, let's
切换颜色。词法分析器与解析器进行通信。
switch colors. The lexical analyzer communicates with the parser. Okay and the
这里的功能是, 词法分析器接受一个字符串。
functionality here is that, the lexical analyzer takes in a string. Typically
存储起来, 也只是一个字节序列然后当解析器听不清时
stored up, also just a sequence of bytes and then when [inaudible] to the parser is
顺序或对, 也就是令牌类, 还有子串, 我想说
sequence or pairs which are the token class. And substring which I would say
这里的字符串, 也就是字符串的集合这是其中的一部分
string here, that, that, of which is the sets of string which is a part of the
和这个类一起输入它在语言中所起的作用, 以及这个
input along with the class the role that it plays in the in the language, and this
一对组合被称为令牌, 例如, 如果我的字符串是f00=42,
pair together is called a token. So for example, if my string is that f00 = 42,
好了, 这就会进入词法分析程序, 我就会讲到
all right, then that will go to the lexical analyzer and that will come, I'll
写在这里, 三个记号, 这些是标识符, 谁？操作员说
write down here, three tokens. And these would be identifier. Who? Operator say
等于。整数, 抱歉, 42, 这里我把这些东西留作字符串
equals. And. Integer, excuse me 42. And here I just left these things as strings
为了强调这些是字符串, 所以这不是第42个数字
to, to emphasize that these are strings. So this is not the number 42 at this point
在时间上, 它是字符串42这是一个在编程中扮演一个整数的角色
in time, it's, it's the string 42 which is a plays an integer role in the programming
语言, 然后这些, 当这个输入的价格是这个
language. And then these, and when the price that takes this input is this
成对的序列, 所以词法分析器本质上是在输入字符串上运行的
sequence of pairs. So the lexical analyzer essentially runs over the input string and
把它分成成对的序列, 每一对都是一个令牌类和a
chunks it up into the sequence of pairs where each pair is a token class and a
原始输入的子串, 当我们从一开始就讲这个例子
substring of the original input. As we turn to the example from the beginning of
视频, 在这里它被写成一个字符串, 我们现在的目标是词法方面的
the video, here it is written out as a string. And our goal now is to lexically
分析这段代码, 我们想要遍历并识别子字符串
analyze this fragment of code. We want to go through and identify the substrings
这是令牌, 也是它们的令牌类, 因此, 要做到这一点, 我们需要
that are tokens and also their token classes. So, to do this, we're gonna need
一些令牌类, 让我们给自己一些可以使用的东西。
some token classes. So let's give ourselves some of those to work with.
我们需要白色空间, 这是一个空格, 新行标签,
We'll need white space. And, and so this is sequences of blanks, new lines tab,
用关键字之类的东西, 我们需要变量, 我们会调用
things like that with the keywords. And we'll need variables which we'll call
标识符, 我们需要整数现在我把这些数字记在这里
identifiers. And we'll need integers and now I'll call those numbers. Here and then
我们将会有一些其他的操作一些其他的类比如open paren
we're going to have some other operations some other classes things like open paren
关闭paren和分号这些都很有趣, 这三个有趣的
close paren, and semi colon and these are interesting. These three ae interesting
因为它们是单字符令牌类, 它是一组字符串
because they're single character token classes that is, is a set of strings but
只是, 在集合中只有一个字符串所以打开的paren对应的是精确的
is only, is only one string in the set so the open paren corresponds to exact
听不清的字符串只包含开放的paren, 通常的标点符号
[inaudible] strings that contain only open paren. So often the punctuation marks of
这门语言都是自己的标记类, 另一个标点符号
the language are in token classes all by themselves. Another piece of punctuation
这里我们要添加的是赋值, 它本身就是一个令牌类
that we'll add here is, is assignments. That will be a token class by itself
因为这是一个很重要的操作, 但是, 双等号是a类
because it's such an important operation. But, the double equals will class as a
这个类的关系运算符把它放在这里, 好了, 现在
relational operator with this class as an operator put it up here. Alright, So now
我们要做的是, 我们要对这个字符串进行标记, 我是
what we're going to do is we're gonna go through and tokenized this string and I'm
为每一个子串写下来, 它是什么类, 你知道, 我只是想
going to write down for each substring. What class it is. You know, I'm just gonna
使用这个类的第一个字母, 它只是为了节省时间, 所以我
use the first letter here of the class. It's indicated just to save time so I
不需要把所有的东西都写出来, 因此, 我们改变颜色, 这样我们就可以在a中做这个
don't have to write everything up. Hence, we change colors so we can do this in a
不同的颜色, 第一个令牌是白色空间令牌, 然后
different color. So, the first token here is white space token and then that
然后是F关键字, 好了, 然后这里有一个空白, 这是另一个
followed by the F keyword. So, okay, And then we have a blank here which is another
空白区域, 然后是开放的paren这是它自己的令牌类所以我就离开
white space and then the open paren which is its own token class so I'll just leave
它在那里识别, 然后我们有一个标识符, 好的, 空格和
it to identify itself there and then we have an identifier. Okay, White space and
然后是一个算子, 双等号, 另一个空白, 这是空白区域
then an operator, the double-equals. Another blank so that's white space
后面是另一个标识符后面是关闭括号, 这里是一个标点符号
followed by another identifier followed by close parens, Again, a punctuation mark in
一个令牌类, 然后我们有三个空白字符, 这些是
a token class by itself. And then we have three white space characters so those are
作为一个白色的空间令牌组合在一起, 然后是另一个标识符
group together as a white space token, Followed by another identifier and more
空格, 然后是另一个字符令牌, 赋值运算符,
white space and then another single character token, the assignment operator,
空格和数字, 然后是sem i冒号, 标点符号和a
white space and a number, And then sem i colon again and punctuation mark and a
令牌类单独使用。两个空格字符可以组合在一起。
token class by itself. Two white space characters can group together. What
下面是一个关键字, 因此它被分类为关键字标记类。
follows in is a keyword, so it gets classified as in the keyword token class.
另一个白色空格字符, 然后是另一个标识符, 实际上
Another run of white space characters and then another identifier. There's actually
这里是一个空白, 我们几乎把它覆盖了没有标记, 赋值运算符
a blank there where we almost covered it up without marks. The assignment operator
它本身在一个令牌类中, 空格, 一个数字, 最后是半冒号
by itself in a token class, white space, a number, and finally the semi colon by
它本身, 还有我们的记号化, 我们已经确定了子串, 我们
itself. And there is our tokenization. We've identified the substrings and we've
也用它的令牌类标记每一个。
also labeled each one with its token class.